[Music]
in this first section on http we're going to start off with just a
very quick overview of the web and http
then we're going to dive down into the
two types of http connections
persistent and non-persistent
connections and
look at the major messages used by http
the request message and the response
message and then finally we'll wrap up
this first
section by taking a look at what are
known as cookies a ways for
state to persist at a server between one
client connection
and another client connection now this  just the first
is just the first
of two parts that we're going to cover on http but we've got a
lot to cover here so let's get started well let's begin our discussion of
the web and http with just a very quick review to set the stage
remember that a web page consists of a
base
html file as well as a set of referenced
objects and each of these objects can be
stored on different web servers
an object can be an html file jpeg image
a java apple
audio file or many other things and the
web page itself as well as the reference
objects are each addressable by what's
known as a url
there's a host name associated with it
and then on that host there's a path
name piece to it
well let's get started with our study of
http and the very first thing to know
is that http adopts the client server
model that we just studied in section
2.1
a client might be a web browser like
firefox or safari or
edge or it might actually be embedded in
a device and you might not even see it
a server might be a traditional web
server that
only serves web pages or a more general
purpose server
like gaia.cs.umass.edu which provides a
number of services
in this animation here we see on the top
pc running the firefox browser
making an http request to a server and
getting a response
back at the bottom we see an iphone
running safari browser also making an
http request
and getting an http response back both
of those browsers are speaking the http
protocol with the apache web server
http uses the transport services
provided by the tcp
protocol and here's how an http
transaction works
the http client your web browser for
example
opens a tcp connection to a web server
using port 80. we'll learn about port
numbers in just a second
one or more messages http messages are
then exchanged between the client and
the server
and then the tcp connection is closed
http is a stateless protocol
this means that the server maintains no
internal state about the ongoing request
there's a single request for an object
and a single reply that's it
there's no worrying about something like
well this transaction has five steps
we're now in step three
and if i fail i'm going to need to roll
back my state to what it was
before this five step transaction
started none of that with http
it's stateless and you might ask why
well because of its simplicity
as we'll see protocols that maintain
state will need to deal with clean up
problems when a multi-step transaction
fails
returning to the initial state and
resolving inconsistent state
there are two types of http connections
what are called persistent connections
and non-persistent connections and it's
important to remember
these http connections between a browser
and a server are different than the tcp
connection which is provided at the
transport layer underneath
in non-persistent http a tcp connection
is opened
at most one object is then sent over the
tcp connection
and the tcp connection is closed
downloading multiple
objects is going to require multiple tcp
connections to be established
and we'll see that it takes a round-trip
time first to open the tcp connection
and then another rtt
to make the request and receive the
response
in persistent http a tcp connection is
again open to the server
but this time multiple objects can be
transferred
serially over the single tcp connection
between the client
and the server once those multiple
objects have been requested and returned
the tcp connection can be closed
persistent http corresponds to http
version 1.1 which is probably the most
common form of http in use today
here's an example of non-persistent http
and operation
let's assume that the user in step 1a
here enters a url
www.sumschool.edu
and asks for a web page that contains text as well as references to
10 jpeg image in that base html file
so in step 1a we see the client
initiating the tcp connection to the
http server
at port 80 at www.sumschool.edu
in step 1b the http server at the host
which has been waiting for a tcp
connection at port 80 accepts this tcp
connection
and notifies the client and notice in
steps one a and one b
no http requests have actually flowed
yet
this happens in step two in step two the
http client
sends the http request message into the
tcp connection that's just been
established
this http message indicates that the
client wants to receive
this base html file in step 3 the
servers now receive this http request
message
and forms the response message that
contains the requested object
and sends this message back to the http
client
after sending the response message in
step 4 the http server closes the tcp
connection
in step 5 the http client receives the
response message containing the html
file
displays the html file parses it finds
the 10 reference
jpeg objects and in step 6 now
it's going to have to repeat the
preceding five steps
for each of the reference jpeg objects
now we can take a look at the response
time for non-persistent http
we can define the response time as the
amount of time from when a user
first enters a url into a browser
until that base html file is received
and displayed
so let's define the rtt the round trip
time as the amount of time
needed for a very small packet to travel
from the client
to the server and back and so we can see
that the non-persistent
http response time per object has the
following components
well one rtt is needed to initiate the
tcp connection
and another rtt a second rtt is needed
for the http request to be transmitted
and received
and for the first bytes of the http
response
to be returned and then finally there's
the amount of time
needed for the server to actually
transmit the file
into its internet connection
and so overall the non-persistent http
response time is two rtt plus whatever amount of time is needed to transmit
the file so we've seen that two rtts are needed to fetch a web
object now multiple objects can often be retrieved in parallel but still two rtts
is well two rtts and you know
two rtts is well two rtts and you know
we really want to get our information as fast as possible so it's possible
using a simple technique to actually cut this latency from two rtts to one
rtt and that's to use a technique known as persistent connection and this is
the way that most web servers are now operating in persistent http http 1.1
the server leaves the connection open after sending the response subsequent http messages between
the same client and server can then be sent over this open connection without
having to wait that rtt to establish a new tcp connection when a client
has a new request to send it sends it as soon as it encounters
a referenced object and so we can see
here how persistent http cuts the
response time
in half to one rdt
now that we've looked at the two styles
of http connections we can dive down
into the details
of the http messages themselves and
remember
way back in section 1.1 we said that a
protocol defines the format and the
order
of messages sent and received among
network entities
and the actions taken when these
messages are sent and received
let's take a look at the http protocol
and let's take a look at its messages
there are two types of http messages
request messages and response messages
let's take a look at a request message
first a request message
starts with a single request line with
that line beginning with a method name
for example
get as shown here a url in this case the
name of the html file being requested
the version of http in this case 1.1
and a new line that is a carriage return
line feed
the single request line is then followed
by a number of header lines that provide
additional information
for example the name of the host where
the request is being made
the type of browser making a request in
this case firefox
the types of objects that can be
accepted and preferred language in this
case u.s
english and the fact that this
connection should be kept alive
the request message ends with an empty
line so as you can see
very human readable
here's the general format for an http
request message
we see the request line followed by
header lines http protocol specification
rfc 7320 is 85 pages long
and has all the details about the
methods header field names and values
fortunately for us as networking
students we don't need to know
all of those details but if we were
implementing an http client or server
we'd have to know
every detail when we looked at the get
message in the previous slide there was
no entity body
that's needed by some request messages
like post which we'll see in a second
that need to send additional information
not in the header fields to the server
here are the four types of http request
messages we've seen the get method
already the post method is used to
upload completed form data to the server
and the put method can be used to upload
a new object to the server
with a given url possibly replacing an
existing object
and last the head method ask for a
response that's
identical to that of a get request but
without the response body
this could be used for example to
determine the size of an object that
would be retrieved
but without actually retrieving that
object
now let's quickly take a look at the
http response message
the response message begins with a
status line and the first thing on the
status line
is the version number of the http
protocol being used
in this example here 1.1 following the
version number are the two most
important pieces of information
in the response message a status code
and a short message
in this case the status code shown is
200 which means that everything went
okay and a short status phrase in this
case
the word ok following the status line
there are response header lines
as in the case of the request message
that provide additional information
for example shown here you can see that
the date and time the response was sent
the type of server is also shown in this
case an apache server version
2.4.6 the last modified field shows the
time when the document was last modified
the content length field shows how long
the document is
and the content type field indicates the
type of object that's being returned
in this case an html document and
finally the body of the object
being returned in this case the html
document itself
and here are just a few of the http
response status codes and phrases
we've already seen the 200 okay
indicating that a request has succeeded
you've probably seen a 404 not found
when a requested document
was not found on the server all of the
response status codes and phrases are
contained
in the rfc document so take a look there
if you're
really interested in learning about all
of the status codes and response phrases
so that wraps up our discussion of http
messages
it's pretty simple as promised and
there's only two types of messages
and as also promised it's pretty human
digestible we could look at those http
messages
and pretty much understand them let's
wrap up our initial study of http
by coming back to this question of
statelessness we said that http
is a stateless protocol as it turns out
it's possible for a web server to
actually maintain some user state
to remember what a user's done in the
past
and how that might influence what a user
wants to do in a current session
by using a technique known as cookies
let's take a look
websites will use cookies to maintain
information about a user
more specifically a user's browser in
between transactions
and there are four components to using
cookies first
a server at some point is going to send
a cookie
to a client the cookie is just a number
and it's contained in a cookie header
line
of an http response message being sent
to a client
then later when the client next makes a
request to that server it will
send along that cookie value to the
server in a cookie header line
now the server is going to remember all
of the requests that's received and the
responses it's sent
associated with that cookie value so
it'll have a history
of the interactions with that user let's
take a look at an example
let's take a look at an example in this
example a client on the left here is
going to make a couple of http requests
to an amazon server for example on the
right
which has a back-end database where it's
going to store cookie-related
information
the client also has cookie information
from other websites it's visited
in this case a cookie from ebay for
example but it doesn't have a cookie
from amazon
yet the client makes a request as usual
to the amazon web server initially
without a cookie
line when the amazon web server gets the
http request
creates a cookie stores the cookie and
the transaction
information in its database and sends an
http response to the client
including a cookie value
now here in the second request by the
client the client includes its cookie
value to amazon
allowing the amazon server to take a
cookie specific action
perhaps taking the first http request
now into account
for example maybe the first transaction
was a request to look at one item of
merchandise and the second http request
wanted to look at a second item of
merchandise
with cookies the second reply could be
crafted to offer the client a deal on
buying
both of those items of merchandise
together
even though the second request only
wanted to look at one particular
piece of merchandise the client comes
back a week later and again provides a
cookie
the server can again take a cookie
specific action
for example it could say hey i missed
you during the past week you sure you
don't want to buy those
items that you looked at during the past
week
so in this example we can see how
cookies can be used
to store state about a user at a website
in between http interactions
given that cookies can be used to store
user state over multiple transactions
they've got lots of uses remembering
that you've authenticated yourself to a
site before
for remembering the contents of your
shopping cart or for making
recommendations
based on past behavior you may have also
read about the many privacy concerns
about cookies  can allow websites to learn a
cookies can allow websites to learn a
lot about you there are what are called third-party cookies that can be put
into your browser and allow websites to establish a common identity across multiple websites
and you may have also heard about the eu's general data protection regulation gdpr
under gdpr cookies that aren't strictly necessary for the operation of a website can
only be activated after you've given your explicit consent for their use and for
the collection of personal data you may have noticed recently that at a lot
of sites before you're able to use
lot of sites before you're able to use
that site you have to agree  to a certain cookie policy
well that wraps up the first part of our
study of the web and http and we've learned a lot already we after
a quick introduction we dove down into the different types of http connections we
studied the request and the response messages and we also took a look at
cookies a way to remember some state on the server side between user interactions
with that server so coming up next in the second part we're going to
take another deeper dive into some additional aspects of improving http performance we're going
to look at web caches we're going to look at the conditional get request
and then finally we're going to look at http version 2 the most recent
version of http and take a quick peek at http version 3  which is coming within the next year or